Finding Aid for United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Detroit records, 1828-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Detroit records 1828-1974
United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Detroit.
852270 Ba 2
Minutes, rosters of ministers, and statistical and financial records; also retired records of individual Presbyterian churches, including the; and miscellaneous synodical files.
13 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the records were received from the Presbytery of Detroit (donor no. 1438 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Synod of Michigan (now the Synod of the Covenant) of the United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. is divided into different geographical presbyteries in Michigan and Ohio. In Michigan, these presbyteries are Detroit, Lake Michigan, Lake Huron, and Mackinac. Over the years, there has been changes to the boundaries of the Synod and of the number and geographical responsibilities of the individual presbyteries.
The Presbytery of Detroit dates back to 1827, when a number of ministers and churches in the Detroit area met together to constitute themselves as a Presbytery. In the 20th Century, the Presbytery of Detroit has worked to meet the social needs of the population of the Detroit metropolitan area. These included a number of outreach programs: community houses in the early 1900's, camp and conference ministries and the establishment of Presbyterian Villages begun in the 1940's, the Detroit Industrial Mission of the 1950's and 60's, and urban church redevelopment and racial ethnic ministries in the 1970's and 80's. Throughout, the Presbytery of Detroit has sought to fulfill its ministerial mission in the ever-changing metropolitan area.
The record group includes record books of defunct Presbyterian churches within the Presbytery. Most of these are Detroit churches: Cadillac Boulevard, Broadstreet United, Third Street Union Mission Sunday School, Church of the Redeemer, Forest Avenue, Marston Avenue, and the Welsh United. Also included are Hamtramck United Presbyterian Church, Waterford Center Presbyterian Church, and Ida Presbyterian Church. A valuable source of information about the churches of the Presbytery is the Church Files series which includes annual reports, membership directories, clippings, and other materials relating to church activities. The Administrative records and topical files is of value for evidence of the church's role in issues of race and poverty. The minutes of Presbytery meetings contain the earliest records of the organization dating back to 1828.
Subjects:
Broadstreet United Presbyterian Church (Detroit, Mich.); Cadillac Boulevard Presbyterian Church (Detroit, Mich.); Church of the Redeemer Presbyterian Church (Detroit, Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Forest Avenue Presbyterian Church (Detroit, Mich.); Hamtramck (Mich.); Hamtramck United Presbyterian Church (Mich.); Ida (Mich.); Ida Presbyterian Church (Mich.); Lakeshore Presbyterian Church (Port Huron, Mich.); Marston Avenue Presbyterian Church (Detroit, Mich.); Port Huron (Mich.); United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A.--Michigan--Detroit.; United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A.--Michigan--Hamtramck.; United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A.--Michigan--Port Huron.; United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A.--Michigan--Waterford Center.; United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Synod of Michigan.; Third Street Union Mission Sunday School (Detroit, Mich.); Waterford Center (Mich.); Waterford Center Presbyterian Church (Mich.); Welsh-Americans--Michigan.; Welsh United Presbyterian Church (Detroit, Mich.); United Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Detroit.
- Individual church and presbyterial organizations
  - Cadillac Blvd. Presbyterian Church (Detroit) records 1949-1963, 5 volumes (Box 1)
  - Broadstreet United Presbyterian Church (Detroit) records 1925-1960, 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Hamtramck United Presbyterian Church records 1960-1966, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - Third Street Union Mission Sunday School (Detroit) records 1867-1893, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - Lakeshore Presbyterian Church, Port Huron Session record December 1961-June 1970, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Church of the Redeemer Presbyterian Church (Detroit) records 1888-1891, undated, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Forest Avenue Presbyterian Church (Detroit) records 1893-1914, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Waterford Center (Oakland County) Presbyterian Church records 1899-1916, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Marston Avenue Presbyterian Church (Detroit) records 1908-1918, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Ida (Monroe County) First Presbyterian Church records 1898-1938, 1 volumes (Box 2)
  - Welsh United Presbyterian Church (Detroit) records 1919-1974, 3 volumes; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Welsh United Presbyterian Church (Detroit) records 1919-1974, 13 volumes (Box 3)
  - Dodge Community House records (Box 4)
  - Presbyterian Neighborhood Services files (Box 4)
- Church files: include annual reports membership directories, etc.
  - Detroit-Redford Avenue Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Detroit-Trumbull Avenue United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Detroit-Village United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Detroit-Ward Memorial United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Detroit-Welsh United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Detroit-Westminster United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Detroit-Winchester Village United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Detroit-Woodward Avenue United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Drayton Plains-Community United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - East Detroit-Covenant United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Ecorse-United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Farmington-United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Ferndale-Drayton Avenue United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Flint Farnumwood United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Fraser Peace United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Garden City-United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Grand Haven-First Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Grosse Ile-United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Grosse Pointe-Memorial United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Grosse Pointe Woods-United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Highland Park-United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Holly-United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Jackson-Westminster United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Lansing-Mt. Hope Avenue Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Lansing-North Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Lincoln Park-United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Livonia-Rosedale Gardens Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Livonia-St. Paul's United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Livonia-St. Timothy United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Ludington-Community Church (Box 5)
  - Mackinaw City-Church of the Straits (Box 5)
  - Menominee-United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Midland-Memorial Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Milford-United Presbyterian Church (Box 5)
  - Monroe-First Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Mt. Clemens-First Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Muir-First Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Muskegon-First Presbyterian Church Northville-United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Orchard Lake-Community Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Peck-Elk United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Plymouth United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Pontiac First Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Pontiac Church of the Atonement (Box 6)
  - Pontiac Joslyn Avenue Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Pontiac Oakland Avenue Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Port Huron-First Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Port Huron-Lake Shores United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Riverview-Presbyterian Church Rochester-University Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Roseville-Erin Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Royal Oak-First Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Royal Oak-First United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Royal Oak-Christ Memorial Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Saginaw-Countryside United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - St. Clair Shores-Faith Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - St. Clair Shores-Lake Shore Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - St. Ignace-Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Shelby-St. Thomas Community Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Southfield-Northbrook United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Southfield-United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - South Lyon United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Taylor Southminster United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Trenton United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Trout Creek-United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Troy-First Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Troy-Northminster Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Utica-United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Walled Lake-Cross Roads Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Warren-First Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Warren-Celtic Cross Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Warren-St. Luke Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Waterford-Lakeland United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Wayne-First Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Wayne-Kirk of our Savior Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - White Lake United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
  - Wyandotte United Presbyterian Church (Box 6)
- Administrative and Topical files
  - Numbered files (Box 6)
  - Numbered files (cont.) (Box 7)
  - Numbered files (cont.) (Box 8)
  - Rev. Claude Williams files 1943-1954, 6 folders (Box 8)
    (Williams was Industrial Chaplain of the Detroit Presbytery and director of the People's Institute of Applied Religion)
  - Angela Davis Defense Fund and the church (Box 8)
  - Industrial Missions
    - Detroit Industrial Mission (Box 8)
    - Flint Industrial Mission (Box 8)
    - Sterling Forest Ministry (Box 9)
    - National Committee for Industrial Missions (Box 9)
  - Sabbatical Study Committee (Box 9)
  - Planning Committees, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Hugh C. White, Jr. (sermons and notes), 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Matthew Thies (Dodge Community House) 1957-1959 (Box 9)
  - Settlement Extension Service memoranda, Matthew Thies files 1956 (Box 9)
  - Institute on Church in Corporate Society (Box 10)
  - Urban missions and ministries and related material (Box 10)
  - Churches of the presbytery book of statistics 1927-1942 (Box 10)
    (include data on membership and giving)
  - Michigan church census studies (Box 10)
  - Historian's files (Box 10)
  - National Black Economic Development 1969 (Box 10)
  - Presbytery newsletter, "Rejoice" (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook containing clippings and photographs of churches within the presbytery (unbound) (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook with clippings concerning the San Antonio meeting of the General Assembly of the United Presbyterian Church 1969 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous newspaper clippings (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 10)
- Minutes of meetings (annual, stated, adjourned, and special)
  - 1828-1840 (Box 11)
  - 1840-1847 (Box 11)
  - 1848-1853 (Box 11)
    (includes lists of churches, ministers, elders, etc., circa 1828-1950s)
  - 1855-1869 (Box 11)
  - 1869-1881 (Box 12)
  - 1881-1893 (Box 12)
  - 1893-1899 (Box 12)
  - 1899-1904 (Box 12)
  - 1904-1912 (Box 12)
  - 1912-1921 (Box 13)
  - 1921-1930 (Box 13)
  - 1931-1940 (Box 13)
- Other Records
  - Benevolent fund ledger 1929-1937 (Box 13)
  - Record book containing annual statistics for the period 1829-1928 (Box 13)